We will see that ultimately, the brain's development, in this dynamic,
will guide and organize all these phenomena of
intracranial membranes
and will support and allow the creation of this reciprocal tension membrane system
in which
all vessels will circulate, at least significant vessels in terms of...
venous flow, to drain
and release
this CO2,
and substances that must
return in a very specific way
and that many problems
actually stem from stasis
with key points that we will study
among others at certain confluences
such as the
pterygoids or
certain transverse venous sinuses at the
occipital floor
where we have gatherings
almost of eight layers
that will form at this level.
It is truly a meeting point,
an important crossroads.
Also at the skull base.
We can say that this craniosacral mechanism
is
important in the sense that
it is one of our
references upon which
we can always rely.
Do I have a good craniosacral mechanism?
Craniosacral-mandibular
from an age when the child straightens up.
When the child begins to have teeth,
the child begins to straighten up.
Teeth are posture sensors.
You will understand something now in your mind,
it will click for you, what I’m going to tell you.
The importance of teeth is that they provide support for
your posture. They really are
supports so that you can breathe
correctly.
The tongue is very important too.
At first,
we look for it, you see
children, they are like this.
They are searching for the tongue, it's very
important. After, the teeth come,
and when they start to have support points,
with the teeth above and below,
the child straightens up.
Okay? And now, you will understand, look, before
the elderly, when they have no more teeth,
how are the elderly?
The teeth, they will say...
You put teeth on them now,
and they straighten up. All these people,
all these elderly people have teeth,
have dentures.
They have supports for breathing.
You ask an old person
who has no teeth, you say, come on, straighten up.
They cannot breathe.
They can no longer smile.
They search for support points for
breathing with their posture so the teeth become posture sensors for
the child’s uprightness and of your posture. It is very important
it’s very important also not to
have a tooth missing on one side. Why? You have a tooth, they remove it, you have one on
the
side that they took out. Why is it very important? If you have a tooth
missing, your tongue
it shifts to the side,
so it slightly
opens its space for the tongue
because it’s really important
the tongue is
magnificent for many things.
It surpasses to the side
here, it comes
to plug the hole
to facilitate your swallowing.
And in fact,
as the tongue is part of the lingual axis
it is part of your axial
longitudinal, what we call
the axis of the
embryonic chain.
This is the primary axis; it is your embryonic chain that terminates at your thumbs and your big toes, it
is your embryonic chain that organizes like this.
And so you will look through your tongue, through your posture, through your teeth to maintain
your balance.
And the eye ultimately will seek its stability in relation to your vestibular system,
with an orientation of 23 degrees like this, a
23-degree orientation like this.
Initially, the inner ear is oriented like this, like
this.
And then, through growth, you seek here.
That’s why children have many ear infections.
Especially if the child is yelled at too much at home.
Observe, the children who have ear infections are the ones who have noise at home.
The first thing I say is, you all need to calm down, ma'am.
No, but I mean, let’s talk maybe a bit quieter.
It is a protection against the water we will put. And then at the same time, they seek to horizontalize
at one point. When they straighten up, they horizontalize, they reach an angle, which is
an angle
that will find the same angle at the heart level, the same angle as the angle
of the Earth. You orient yourself in relation to your universe through your angular planes. You
seek
stability. The body is always a bit forward too. If you look, there
is always a
certain degree where it is like this.
In fact, if you look at someone, you will see in relation to their axis, they have a tilt
tendency that I know, you swallow up to 1 or 2 liters a day, you do 25,000 breaths
a day, your heart beats 100,000 times a day, that is a digestive rhythm, that is a
respiratory rhythm, that is a cardiac rhythm, you see, in fact what we will
do is
situate ourselves in our different rhythms, cardiac rhythm, my digestive rhythm which is
really good. It’s related
also to
hearing.
Because
the diverticula, that will be for next time,
it's Meckel's cartilage
which continues with the inner ear.
You have the styloid process which continues
with the inner ear system.
I will explain this in detail next time.
We will see how
we can bring it into our midline
and how we can clear up the system.
It is done like this. It’s embryology.
It’s a study of the face.
Already, these two magical bones which are the sphenoid and the occiput,
we will see that they are completely subjected to this craniosacral mechanism.
It’s schematic, but it shows us, you see,
look what will happen simply in a flexion and extension at the level of the teeth.
Look, there are people who completely wear down the anterior part,
people who completely wear down the posterior part.
It’s really important to understand this pattern.
And then we will see that you have the occipito-lingual chain,
which is really a very important chain for the complete dynamics of the body.
It’s a midline, it is almost indirectly part of a continuity
of our body.
It’s a representation that is not anatomical, but it is
really a support point.
This lingual complex and the tongue, it’s the bud of the heart.
The tongue will give rise with respect to the foramen cæcum to the thyroid.
The thyroid will electrify your words. One day, you will have to
speak with your frontal sinuses, meaning you will have to face
front. It’s at that moment that some people face too much
or some people do not face enough. It’s a matter of throat.
It’s for this reason that at a certain point, we no longer need
words. We speak completely in frequencies. There are people who simply give frequencies.
Like that, for example, mantras become frequencies. They become archetypal sounds
that re-neutralize and bring you back into a conscious archetype of the collective unconscious.
Thus, they re-neutralize the words. Mantras are made to stop your internal
incessant discourse.
Show the occipito-lingual chain. Look
at the power.
It interferes here. It’s the lingual chain.
You will have the chain that is normally sphenoidal-axial.
It’s a chain anticipating your life.
It’s a descending chain here.
We will talk about this next time in the viscerocranium.
To show you ultimately all this mechanical plan of
where we see the global action of all these lines of force present
They are descending sequences.
We have the viscerocranium and we have the neurocranium.
We see that between the two, we have this base of the skull.
This base of the skull is a very important element for development
and it is actually linked to the base of the skull.
It’s an articulation between the aortas and the brain.
Already the skull takes shape here; it is starting to resemble, we already have almost
a future image, it’s the precursor image
for the skull, with the brain already having real
importance,
because it is the one that drives the system with a differential growth speed
that will bring this folding of the embryo with the process of...
telencephalon, of the diencephalon
that comes from the prosencephalon,
the mesencephalon, and then behind
we have the rhombencephalon which
will give this
dynamic with the
metencephalon and the thing underneath
the brain. It’s an articulation
between the brain and
the aorta. At one moment,
we see that there is a flexion.
And in this flexion, which will
organize here, here’s the key
after the recruitment
of the embryo, meaning this folding of the encephalon towards the front, the mesenchyme
which is under the mesencephalon becomes perpendicular with
respect to the longitudinal axis of the embryo.
There is a compression here. This sub-mesencephalic orientation
manifests
in a development we call the sub-mesencephalic septum which is connected
between the front and
the back of the brain, so you see it compresses here and it’s the heart with
its aortas and the amniotic cavity
that organizes this space, the septum that
develops here, you see, becomes the base
of the skull and it’s there that we see at one moment in this flexion if now I
do the
backward flexion. There is a small pocket here. It’s a little endodermal pocket.
It’s a tissue, here,
the black tissue is intestine, so it’s endoderm. Do you know what that means?
It will become this little pocket. Do you know what this little pocket is called?
It’s called Rathke's pouch, with back here, the
Seessel pouch,
but well, Rathke's pouch. And this Rathke pouch will become at the base
of the skull one of the most important structures called the anterior pituitary.
I remind you that the pituitary is made of two parts,
one neurological part and one digestive part.
And well, this part, this meeting of the two will form the pituitary and at
the beginning, you have this pouch that we call Rathke's pouch which comes,
now we do the reverse you see, and I open
and I reduce the size,
I put the embryo back in its initial phase,
this pouch like this,
you see. If I just take this small pouch,
here like this, you see it, huh,
and I open it, it becomes this,
it flattens out again.
And in fact, it’s the flexion of the embryo
with the heart’s restraint
that leads at one point to this fold
like a suction field of the tissue,
a suction field, as we saw, that takes
and absorbs and comes
to fit in the base
of this skull in its anterior part. And this will form what we call
the pre-pituitary.
At the same moment, you have a posterior part
that comes, which is the infundibulum,
that comes
from the upper part of the brain,
same suction field,
and which comes to meet to form the
neurological pituitary. And the two
together form the pituitary with this whole
orchestra conductor because that’s really where, and
we send hormones, and we send
stuff, and we make a mess, etc. It’s a neurological endocrine conductor
immense. And where does the conductor settle? On the skull base
which is what? A support point.  So you already have
a development on this base
of the skull.
which is both purely endodermal, thus digestive,
and at the same time neurological.
This means that this base of the skull knows the environment of
the brain and the environment of your digestive system.
It’s a balance between your brain and your digestive system.
It’s a balance between the neurocranium and the viscerocranium.
That’s where we see too much flexion, too much extension,
this opening, this movement of the base of the skull,
where you have these torsion phenomena.
But all this will eventually reflect on the functioning,
little by little, of this pituitary function.
The function needs movement.
The function is merely a repetition of a primary embryological movement,
at one point.
That’s why the true function is a movement
of motility
that will organize
a movement of mobility
that will organize a movement of motricity.
So this base of the skull
is not just an articulation
in the beginning between my brain
growing and my aortas
that are slowing down,
the whole mechanism makes it that one of the first things
that will happen is
whoops I have a small pouch that forms
that we call Rathke's pouch
that will create part of the pituitary.
Here, and at the same time
it’s a field of
contusion on a metabolic level
you see, as we saw this morning
since it’s two tissues
that completely contract
to a field that was right behind
you see, with a field
we had seen the fields of retraction
we had seen fields like this, but initially
it’s a young cartilaginous tissue
that develops there
on an axis
and it will develop what we call
the pituitary cartilage, the paracordal cartilage, and the precordal cartilage
forward, which will be precursors on cartilaginous nodes to
create your occipital base, your sphenoid, and your ethmoid in space.
And later, we will see a part of your petrous pyramids and
later we will see how within this developmental movement, this time,
of the brain in its stage.
brain development, that the whole process of the frontal, parietal, of the
occiput, upper part,
until completing the phase of your temporals. It’s a succession. I
take here, it flips,
and we do this. Then it advances, it will become,
you see, pituitary cartilage,
okay, we see the color, senonian cord. Paracordal cartilage next to
it’s even a notochord? Okay, no worries.
What is it? Basilar, occipital part.
Ah!
My notochord, is it here?
It’s going up there. It’s between what?
It’s between what?
What is it?
It’s just a response. And what comes to settle on it?
What?
My pituitary.
That’s the glandular plan.
Cartilaginous compression and on top I have a bit of glandular that is
completely dependent on everything that happens because this point is actually called the zero point. Let’s say there’s tension
on the
membrane, I know everything that’s happening here and below I feel the other making
lumps, I feel my pituitary, I feel my digestive system, I have my nervous system
and these are membrane
tensions that are in balance. Here there’s a deficit at the blood level,
you see. I feel everything that happens.
You move your... Just move your leg back, I feel it. You, you raise your
arm up, your arm tire, I feel it. You, you lower your head, I
feel it.
You, I feel everything you feel.
The pituitary knows everything that’s happening on a glandular level, on a
bony, cartilaginous basis
and we will see that it knows everything on a
membranous level.
The foramen magnum, here,
with
what we call the crista galli,
the cribriform plate, we see
Meckel's cartilage, with the areas
here, the acoustic meatus,
the jugular foramen which
When we sometimes look for keys between the jugular foramen and the
jugular and the acoustic meatus,
it’s a key that I give you here.
There is also the sella turcica
which is here.
That’s what’s interesting.
Look closely at this junction here with the mouth and jaw.
It’s tinnitus.
Pachymeninge, leptomeninge.
Let’s start over.
Do you remember the formation
of the neural tube?
Now let’s add an element.
The neural tube that starts
to form.
Notochord.
What do I have here around
that’s organizing?
What do I have?
The carotid.
At the beginning of the carotid arteries, somewhere...
And what do these carotids belong to?
What do they belong to?
And so, here, there are still plenty of meso.
And you know what happens here, in this movement?
Well, the meso, which is below, here,
it undergoes a metabolic field here,
of retention.
At first, it’s a little there, like this,
As a stage, because it’s either a dilation field or a retention field,
it can also depend on the space and time in which we find ourselves.
And here, we have a stage where the tissue that is here, it will
undergo a field
where it will receive like a stress from the tissue
we see here.
There, hop, it starts there, here, and then we see here.
it starts to form an ectomeninge.
It’s the peak, if you want,
of the dural layer.
You look at it here,
not only is it here,
but it’s here too.
All along,
it’s like this, you see,
all the way along. And here,
these are cross-sections.
And if I make a cross section,
sagittal-wise, like the neural crest
all along.
I see here a field
that we call the ectomeninge
that is actually linked to the growth speed
differential with
the relationship I have concerning
my notochord, which will form
my neural tube, and the neural tube
will be below
going along its axis, already by a tissue, by an envelope that comes to surround it,
and that will initially close for the first time,
like we saw at the level of the lower cranial part, here, up there,
and then it will form the entire length, like this,
to close at my anterior neuropores and posterior neuropores,
on the 26th, 28th day, it closes,
at the same time I have the reintegration of my external coelom.
external into an internal coelom.
These meninges, you imagine at first,
are just wrapped
And it grows. And when I have my process
of telencephalization here,
like this,
you see? And then it does this.
And then it does like this.
And what will it do?
It will form
my leaf
of my system here since.
the midline here which will form the crista galli, my two prosencephalons
come closer
along the midline, and then it will follow the whole process here, I have a fold behind at the
level
that we saw, it was the posterior fold which will form here at the back this
what we call the cerebellar tent,
and up there it will entirely form the shape,
of the brain, which is a process of cerebralization
given by telencephalization
during the straightening of the embryo. The membranes will follow
the movement, as we had seen that it followed
the ventricular systems, and indeed it will follow
the development of the brain and organize
the dural head here that is developing, and we see
that I have the entire organization
in compartmental
of my tent
of my falx of the brain
of my tent of the cerebellum
and of my falx of the cerebellum
which follows, there it continues here
you see what I mean?
Let’s say I can go inside
it continues
all around my brain
it wraps it up
it’s a wrapping
gift of the brain
with indeed at one moment
a double layer
a layer
visceral type layer,
what we call the visceral dura mater,
and a parietal dura mater layer.
Okay?
Let’s go to an earlier stage.
Do you remember, right from the beginning,
when my brain grows,
it’s initially like this, it closes,
and then it bends, when it bends,
it will first form
three vesicles.
And then it’s just before the process of telencephalization.
Okay?
So if we want to do the movement of the brain,
we advance
at the beginning, we do the three vesicles
and then telencephalization
the great straightening
before that you have this flexion
cervical, etc.
but there the big movement is
I advance like this
and I do this
okay
I come back and I settle down
at the base of
the skull
that these brain vesicles
it’s the ectomesoderm.
We saw already very quickly
that outwardly, this ectomesoderm,
it completely wraps my nervous system.
Are we in agreement?
And that is meso.
This brain is completely wrapped in meso.
Okay?
So it’s completely wrapped up, it forms a tissue that is completely wrapped.
It’s the wrapping of the brain.
These are candies.
Here in front, since there will be two vesicles, there is a kind of sheath.
A densification in the tissue, very strong.
And here too, it’s a very strong densification.
But it’s strong, meaning that...
If I take a tissue and I could take it, I
pull it all out and deposit it like this and we see a bit what’s happening, you see that on it, it’s not that full, there are areas like this that are very hard, you see, these are sheaths
that we call dural belts.
So there are anterior, middle, and posterior dural belts here, especially with
these densifications here.
So if I make a cut of the brain, of the dura mater,
there is a layer that is parietal, and here visceral,
in relation to the brain,
and above, it’s always the same mesodermic tissue, at
the beginning, but with metabolic fields that will have changed,
that is to say changes in density of polymetroic liquid, etc. which will at one point here make
the tissue that is here it’s always
mesoderm and at a certain stage it will become bone and
it’s in this tissue that will be found
this densification you see that will be called
the areas of dural ganglia, which are very interesting
and very important.
We find ourselves here.
And all these dural sheaths,
you see, here, all these sheaths
are like
rings, they are not in the visceral layer. I’ve taken
here, and now, I’m going to
add another element here.
which will be the bony tissue.
Okay?
The or the lobe.
These three rings are there, like that.
And they are all, all, oriented,
all oriented towards my skull base.
Whether it’s the visceral dura mater,
they orient to be organized towards
this base of the skull,
which is an enormous location on a membranous tension
membrane,
intramembranous, extramembranous.
We saw that it was a concentration of mesenchyme
between the ectoderm and the endoderm,
between the heart and the vessel, and the brain, thus
in another way between the hecto and the meso,